<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-11-22T18:11:27-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex Gurvich</title><subtitle>Hydejack is a boutique Jekyll theme for hackers, nerds, and academics, with a focus on personal sites that are meant to impress.
</subtitle><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Astronomy on Tap: Chicago</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/outreach/astronomy-on-tap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Astronomy on Tap: Chicago" /><published>2022-08-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T13:30:06-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/outreach/astronomy-on-tap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/outreach/astronomy-on-tap/"><![CDATA[<p>Astronomy on Tap is an international public outreach effort that combines a love of science and trivia with a love of beer.
The Chicago chapter was originally split between Northwestern and the University of Chicago, but the UoC based group went defunct back in 2018. 
That’s the same year I ascended to <em>host-star</em>, the AoT title for chief organizer of a chapter. 
As host star, I help out by coordinating with venues, choosing and inviting speakers, writing trivia, engaging with audience members during events, and sometimes even giving talks myself.</p>

<p>Nowadays, we are at Begyle Brewing in Ravenswood every ~8 weeks.
You can learn more about Astronomy on Tap in Chicago, including when our next event is, by checking out our
<a href="https://www.facebook.com/aotchicago">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.twitter.com/aotchicago">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://astronomyontap.org/locations/chicago-il/">our homepage</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Astronomy on Tap is an international outreach organization, I was the leader of the Chicago chapter!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/outreach/aot_chicago/bkg_aot_coaster.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/outreach/aot_chicago/bkg_aot_coaster.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Galaxy formation</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/subjects/research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Galaxy formation" /><published>2022-08-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T13:30:06-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/subjects/research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/subjects/research/"><![CDATA[<p>hello this is text</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="subjects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[hello this is text]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/research/vpb/bkg_pretty_threegal_slice.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/research/vpb/bkg_pretty_threegal_slice.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Firefly</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/visualization/firefly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Firefly" /><published>2022-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T14:05:31-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/visualization/firefly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/visualization/firefly/"><![CDATA[<p>Firefly is a browser-based 3D interactive data visualization software for particle-like data. 
I co-created it in partnership with Aaron Geller, a research faculty member (and dataviz guru) at Northwestern’s Center for Interdisciplinary Exploration and Research in Astrophysics (CIERA) where I am currently a graduate student.</p>
<figure style="width:50%; float:right; height:auto; margin:10px">
  <img src="/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firefly/hot_accretion.png" />
  <figcaption>
    hot gas raining down onto a cold disk in a redshift z=0 Milky Way-mass galaxy, visualized with Firefly using velocity vectors, a temperature colormap, and temperature &amp; density filters. 
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Firefly visualizations, once built, can be explored by simply visiting a URL without any prior installation. 
Making a new Firefly visualization is simple with the Python Data Pre-processor (PDPP) we provide. 
Though Firefly has mostly been used for visualizing simulations of galaxy formation (my research focus),  if you can load your data into three numpy arrays you can visualize it in Firefly!
Because Firefly runs in a web-browser, it automatically works on (almost) any operating system or device (including smartphones and iPads). 
Firefly also works in VR, combining stereoscopic views with gyroscopic controls to allow users to walk through their data in the real world using a Google cardboard.</p>

<figure style="width:50%; float:left; height:auto; margin:10px">
  <img src="/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firefly/gaia_lane.png" />
  <figcaption>
    Gaia DR3 in Firefly where each point is a real star colored by its observed BP-RP color. 
    <a target="_blank" href="http://firefly.rcs.northwestern.edu/">
      Available here.
    </a>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Firefly can visualize up to tens-of-millions of particles at once, but for even larger datasets (we’ve tested up to one billion particles) users can take advantage of our progressive rendering scheme which only loads data which lies in the camera’s field of view. 
This is accomplished using a novel data indexing scheme in the PDPP that links the data’s position in realspace to its location on disk using an octree. 
Using this method, we have visualized all of the stars in Gaia DR3, just over one billion stars.</p>

<p>Demos, documentation, and the code paper are all available on the <a href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/Firefly">code’s homepage</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Firefly, users can explore their data by panning, zooming, rotating, filtering, and colormapping just by visiting a URL.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firefly/four_view_banner.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firefly/four_view_banner.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rapid galactic disk settling</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/research/disk-formation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rapid galactic disk settling" /><published>2022-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T13:30:06-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/research/disk-formation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/research/disk-formation/"><![CDATA[<p>A prediction of the the FIRE simulations is that the progenitors of star forming Milky Way-mass disk galaxies are irregular galaxies with time-variable (“bursty”) star formation rates (SFRs). In the simulations, the SFR can change by a factor of 30 in as little as 100 Myr at high redshift, in contrast to the relatively time-steady SFR at low-redshift that remains constant to ~10-20%.</p>

<p>The physics that drive this transition is still not certain. In our collaboration, we are investigating the interplay between the circumgalactic medium (CGM) and interstellar medium (ISM) in this context. Recently, our group has shown that the inner CGM virializes and becomes thermally supported (forming a hot halo) at the same time the SFR becomes time-steady. It is possible that the formation of a hot halo is integral to enabling a disk to remain stable by 1) providing pressure confinement of stellar feedback driven outflows and 2) providing a smooth source of accretion onto the galactic disk. In addition to the coincident formation of a hot halo and steadying of the SFR, there are a number of other properties that change at or near the same time. Our current analysis seeks to explore these factors and isolate the key processes at play and the chain of events leading to stable galactic disk.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ADS link]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/research/disk_formation/bkg_disk_settling_stamps.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/research/disk_formation/bkg_disk_settling_stamps.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CIERA Mentorship Network</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/advocacy/ciera-mentorship/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CIERA Mentorship Network" /><published>2022-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-18T14:17:25-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/advocacy/ciera-mentorship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/advocacy/ciera-mentorship/"><![CDATA[<!--
Mentorship is important for helping people feel like they belong and for giving them advice and making social connections.  
If the pairing is not so great then the relationship can do more harm than good. 
-->
<p>Traditional mentorship structures pair mentors/mentees into “dyads” but there are many axes to mentorship  (emotional, professional, scientific, social, etc.) and it is a lot to expect a single mentor to fulfill all these different needs .</p>
<figure style="width:50%; float:right; height:auto; margin:10px">
  <img src="/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/ciera_mentorship/mentor_lunch.jpg" />
  <figcaption>
    The first mentor network cohort meeting at our monthly lunch to discuss mentorship tools and strategies.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>It would be better instead if mentees had an network of mentors that extended beyond their main thesis advisor and indeed such a network was a popular request in the climate survey of our department.
As a result, CIERA’s Social Justice Initiative Coordinating Committee (SJCC) organized the Mentorship Action Team (MAT). 
As a member of the MAT I used my experience from starting the peer mentorship program in <a href="/docs/advocacy/pagsc/">PAGSC</a> to guide the creation of this broader mentorship program. 
In particular I emphasized the need for concrete mentorship support to persist past the initial phase of matching, and helped to build a library of mentorship resources (e.g. articles, guides, and example mentorship agreements). 
To enhance the impact of these resources, the MAT hosts a monthly lunch to discuss mentorship best practices and to give mentors and mentees an opportunity to meet.
Participation in our mentorship network is not required to attend the monthly lunch so that even those members of the department who did not sign up can benefit from exposure to the materials we provide.</p>

<figure style="width:50%; float:left; height:auto; margin:10px">
  <img src="/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/ciera_mentorship/mentor_network.png" />
  <figcaption>
    An example network of mentors and mentees generated using survey data.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Another major contribution I made to the MAT was in the matching algorithm. 
I led the code development and testing for a network graph theory approach to matching mentors and mentees based on survey data. 
The basic idea is to use a Monte Carlo approach of “randomly” assigning mentees and mentors (with some constraints that prioritize junior members).
By defining quantitative goodness-of-fit metrics on each proposed network, we can take the “optimal” network.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="advocacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I helped design a hierarchical extended mentorship network powered by network graph theory.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/ciera_mentorship/bkg_ciera_logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/ciera_mentorship/bkg_ciera_logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PAGSC</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/advocacy/pagsc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PAGSC" /><published>2022-08-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-18T17:26:23-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/advocacy/pagsc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/advocacy/pagsc/"><![CDATA[<p>The Northwestern Physics and Astronomy Graduate Student Council (PAGSC) is an amazing community of graduate students that helps make life better in the Northwestern Physics and Astronomy department. 
PAGSC is many things but at its core it’s a force for positive change in the department.
PAGSC is split into 7 sub-committees: quality of life, international students, master’s students, outreach, equity &amp; inclusion, TA, and curriculum headed by an executive committee of three: president, secretary, and treasurer.</p>

<p>I sat on the executive committee as 3 years (and was president most recently) and was chair of the outreach committee for the past 5 years.
As an executive committee member and committee chair I met with the department chair quarterly to discuss systemic issues of concern to the department. 
For example, I advocated for and co-served as the first graduate student liaison(s) for the faculty search committee and defined the process by which graduate students interview and give feedback about faculty candidates. 
I also designed a peer mentorship program to match incoming first year students with more senior graduate students and organized extracurricular professional development workshops (and in some cases delivered them myself). 
I also helped write our department’s code of conduct, helped start (and proudly named) our E&amp;I committee’s monthly “Stuff we don’t talk about (but really should) ft. bagels and coffee,” and successfully negotiated the conversion of surplus office space into a graduate study lounge.
As the outreach committee chair, I helped design a set of recommendations for the protocol for the creation of new outreach programs centered on social justice and inclusion, organized outreach programs for a local middle school, and coordinated volunteers for one-off outreach activities.</p>
<figure style="width:50%; float:right; height:auto; margin:10px">
  <img src="/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/pagsc/fireboat.jpeg" />
  <figcaption>
    The second annual boat cruise, a tradition I began as president of PAGSC. We had nearly 100 sailors on our last cruise, so proud of our grad student community!
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>PAGSC is also responsible for planning social events subsidized by the department like movie and game nights, ice skating, and tickets to Cubs games. 
As president of PAGSC, I formalized the procedure by which big ticket “special events” were planned and budgeted and started the tradition of chartering a boat cruise (partially subsidized by the department; tickets are usually ~$20/head) for graduate students to kick off the year and welcome incoming graduate students.
These events are an important social glue that helps bind the department and cross group boundaries in order to build cohesion and help graduate students make friends in a new environment.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="advocacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I helped lead the Physics and Astronomy Graduate Student Council, our department's graduate student self-advocacy organization.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/pagsc/bkg_pagsc_logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/advocacy/pagsc/bkg_pagsc_logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Vertical pressure balance</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/research/vertical-pressure-balance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vertical pressure balance" /><published>2022-08-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T13:30:06-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/research/vertical-pressure-balance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/research/vertical-pressure-balance/"><![CDATA[<p>If the gas in galaxies were allowed to collapse freely it would be entirely converted into stars within just a few hundred million years (i.e. 100% of the gas would be converted to stars per free-falll time). Instead, we see that stars form very inefficiently over the course of billions of years. This inefficiency is parameterized by the observed Kennicutt-Schmidt (KS) relation, a well known observational fact that the surface density of molecular gas and the star formation rate surface density in star forming galaxies is tightly correlated.  The normalization of the KS relation reveals that star formation proceeds very inefficiently, at a rate of approximately 1-2% per free-fall time. However, the physics by which star formation is regulated to this inefficient state are uncertain.</p>

<p>One class of “dynamical equilibrium” models posits that the star formation rate is connected to the gas surface density by means of pressure. One can derive the KS relation (with both the correct slope and normalization) by equating the weight of the overlying gas at the midplane to the pressure generated by stellar feedback from recent star formation. One benefit of this class of models over other explanations for the KS relation is that they naturally predict variation in the slope of the KS relation (a poorly understood but observed phenomenon) as a function of galaxy composition (in particular, the gas fraction).</p>

<p>Using the FIRE simulations to test the of dynamical equilibrium theory, we find that the weight is balanced by the pressure across the face of the disk. I find that the total pressure is dominated by turbulent pressure from the warm and cold phases near the midplane and thermal pressure from the hot phase at above a few (4-5) gas-density-scale-heights. Intriguingly, the FIRE simulations may additionally show that scatter in the KS relation at fixed gas surface density may correspond 1-1 with deviations from vertical pressure balance though direct evidence of a hard link is difficult to prove.</p>

<p>For more details, see the paper.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ADS link]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/research/vpb/bkg_pretty_threegal_slice.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/research/vpb/bkg_pretty_threegal_slice.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Data visualization</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/subjects/visualization/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data visualization" /><published>2022-08-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-05T19:21:14-05:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/subjects/visualization</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/subjects/visualization/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="subjects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firestudio/bkg_firestudio.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firestudio/bkg_firestudio.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRE studio</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/visualization/FIRE-studio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRE studio" /><published>2022-08-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T17:09:47-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/visualization/FIRE-studio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/visualization/FIRE-studio/"><![CDATA[<p>FIRE Studio was inspired by a student I worked with who took a screenshot of figure from a paper and put it on their poster because they wanted a pretty image of a simulation they were studying. 
I thought to myself, this isn’t right. 
The power to visualize images should belong to everyone and so I set out to write a convenient and sensible API for making publication quality images that you could plot stuff on top of. 
Thus, FIRE Studio was born. 
FIRE Studio is named as such because I love movies (science ones but also like, actual movies) and I wanted users to feel like they were in the editing booth turning knobs to make the most fantastic version of their figure/movie (now I mean the science kind) they could.
There are cameras, and “productions” (pre-built visualization scripts that people can riff off of) and utilities for time interpolating data using a novel slope-limiting scheme to avoid spurious artifacts when making high framerate movies (thanks Phil for the inspiration!).</p>

<p>FIRE Studio has a couple of different “modes” (or studios, as I call them).
Users can make column density projections, “two color” projections where the hue is set by one quantity like temperature and the brightness is set by another like density, “three color” projections where different quantities (usually mass in different temperature bins) are projected and colormapped independently and then the R, G, and B channels are blended, and luminosity + dust attenuation maps (mock Hubble images).
Each of these modes shares a common underlying API for setting up the image and can easily be plotted in matplotlib axis objects so you can compose or plot ontop of them.</p>

<p>More information, tutorials, and the code itself can be found <a href="alexbgurvi.ch/FIRE_studio">on it’s homepage</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[FIRE Studio is a package I wrote to allow anyone to make publication quality images of simulation data. Power to the people!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firestudio/bkg_firestudio.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/visualization/firestudio/bkg_firestudio.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dearborn Observatory</title><link href="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/outreach/dearborn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dearborn Observatory" /><published>2022-08-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T13:30:06-06:00</updated><id>https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/outreach/dearborn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/outreach/dearborn/"><![CDATA[<p>Every week the Dearborn Observatory is open to the public on Friday nights from 8:00pm-10:00pm for observing and a tour of the telescope run by graduate students; as it has been for the past 130 years!
Separately, on the last Friday of every month graduate students and post-docs give outreach lectures and answer questions.
These are great opportunities for graduate students to get their feet wet doing outreach and build up some confidence. 
I regularly volunteer to operate the Dearborn Telescope for the public observing sessions as well as host the Astronomer Evenings once or twice a quarter.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Gurvich</name><email>agurvich@u.northwestern.edu</email></author><category term="outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Dearborn Observatory has brought the night sky to Evanston since 1890! I help staff the observing and public talk programs.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/outreach/dearborn/bkg_dearborn.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://alexbgurvi.ch/docs/assets/img/subjects/outreach/dearborn/bkg_dearborn.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>